人类经历了10万年
It took the earth's population a hundred thousand years
才繁衍出10亿人口
to reach a billion people.
在随后的100年 人口增长到20亿
And then just, a hundred more to reach 2 billion.
再翻一番 只花了50年
And only 50 years to double again...
在70年代 人口增至40亿
double again to four billion in 1970.
现在 我们快要达到80亿了 80亿
We're nearly at 8 billion now. ... 8 billion now.
我们正通过延长人均寿命的方式自我毁灭
We are destroying the very means by which life is extended.
每一次全球性的瘟疫灾难都可以被归咎
Every single global ill that plagues the Earth can be traced back...
被归咎于人口的过剩 人口过剩
traced back to human overpopulation... human overpopulation.
为什么我们还不付诸行动
What didn't we demand any action?
我们大量砍伐 倾倒垃圾 挥霍消费 肆意破坏
we clear cut, we dump, we consume, we destroy.
地球上半数的动物物种业已消亡
Half the animal species on earth have vanished
在过去40年里被灭绝 40年
vanished for the last 40 years... 40 years.
我们仍在侵略自然环境
and still we keep attacking our own environment!
非到大难临头 才得深刻教训 ... 留心关注
it doesn't take a catastrophe to learn our lesson... to get our attention
唯有痛苦方可改变行为
Nothing changes behaviour like pain.
或许只有痛苦 才能拯救我们
Maybe pain can save us.
有一个开关
There is a switch,
若你打开
if you throw it,
地球上半数人口会死亡
half the people on earth will die.
但反之 人类将在一百年内灭绝
But if you don't, the human race will be extinct in a hundred years.
你会怎么做
What would you do?
人类就像人体内的癌症
Mankind is the cancer in its own body.
你有拯救芸芸众生的切肤博爱吗
Do you love humanity enough to save it?
为防万一 他们捉住我
In case, they find me,
我给你留下了一串指引
I left you a path.
但它是最艰险的征程
The hardest one yet.
坎坷尽头 横亘炼狱
Inferno will be at the end
你是我的应急计划
You are my contingency plan.
你是人类最后的希望
You are humanity's final hope.
请确保地狱的降临
Make sure Inferno is unleashed.
寻找 就寻见 (圣经 马太福音 第7章 第7节)
Seek and find
佛罗伦萨巴迪亚教堂, 佛罗伦萨, 意大利
Badia Fiorentina (Church), Florence, Italy
追了一路
A long road.
却跑来这里
but here we are.
相比美国人 我更棒些
Better me, than the Americans.
接下来你要向我坦白 它在哪里
You're going to want to tell me where it is.
没错 布沙尔先生
Yes, Mr. Bouchard.
我知道我会的
I know I will.
告诉他们
Tell them,
人类是灾 地狱为解
"Humanity is the disease, Inferno is the cure."
叛徒
Traitor!
受难吧 罪人们 为汝之孽付出代价
Suffer, you sinners. Pay for your sins.
为汝之孽付出代价
Pay for your sins.
受难吧 罪人们 为汝之孽付出代价
Suffer, you sinners. Pay for your sins.
丢魂失魄
Ruin of souls...
- 请稍等 - 怎么回事 ...
- One moment, please - What is going ...
- 发生了什么 - 布鲁克斯医生
- What is happening - Dr. Brooks
抛弃所有的希望
Abadon all hope
所有希望
All hope ...
兰登先生 我是布鲁克斯医生
Mr. Langdon, I'm Dr. Brooks.
我会做些检查 不必担心
I'm going to do a few checks, nothing to worry about.
咱们把它扔掉 好吗
Let's get rid of this, shall we?
您知道今天是周几吗
Do you know what day of the week it is?
周六
Saturday.
今天周一 6月28号
It's Monday, 28th of June.
周一 6月28号
Monday, 28th of June.
您知道我们在哪儿吗
Do you know where we are?
波士顿
Boston.
麻省总医院
Massachusetts General (Hospital)
您最后能记起的事情是什么
And what's the last thing you can remember?
我 呃 我在校园里
I uh... I was on campus.
一切都好模糊 我看不清楚
Everything is blur. It's out of focus.
我是不是遇到了什么意外
Was I in some kind of an accident?
我们会弄清楚的
We'll get to that.
您有没有人需要帮忙通知的
Is there someone we should call for you?
没
No.
您的妻子 家人
Your Wife? Family?
不 不 我没结婚
No. No. I'm not married.
兰登教授 你的头部受创
Professor Langdon, you're suffering from a head trauma.
您似乎有轻微的逆行性失忆
You appeared to have a mild retrograde amnesia
我们做了个CT扫瞄 没有发现颅内出血
We've done a CT scan, there's no evidence of intracranial bleeding.
一切都挺好 会恢复的
Which is very reassuring. Non-terminal.
试着放松下来
Just try to relax.
神经系统方面 看样子没问题
Neurologically, you seem to be fine.
您的记忆会在随后几天恢复
Your memory will return over the next several days.
那么我们 ... 我们就安心静养吧
So we'll... we'll wait and watch.
能麻烦你关下灯吗
Could you turn off the lights please.
没问题
Of course.
若是头部创伤严重 导致脑挫裂伤 那...
If the head trauma was bad enough to cause a cerebral contusion, then...
麻烦你 ... 麻烦你关下灯好吗
Could you please ... Could you please turn off the lights?
我在 ... 佛罗伦萨 ... 来干什么
What am I... doing... in Florence?
那是个大教堂 是佛罗伦萨旧宫 对吗
That's a Duomo. That's the Palazzo Vecchio, isn't it?
对的
Yes.
怎么 ... 我怎么来这儿的
How... How did I get here?
3小时前 你头部带伤 跑来我们的急诊室
You came to our emergency room 3 hours ago with a head wound.
我 ... 我是不是还有位女伴
Was I... Was I with a woman?
没 一位出租车司机送您来的
No, a cab driver brought you in.
没拿钱包 没有手机 没带身份证
No wallet. No phone. No ID.
你怎么知道我名字
How do you know my name?
咱俩见过
We've met.
我在伦敦帝国学院听过你的演讲 后面还聊了下
I saw you lecture at the Church in Imperial College London, we spoke afterwards,
您待我很亲切
you were very nice to me.
我们见过
We've met.
抱歉 那样讲不大恰当
Sorry, that's not quite fair.
那时候我9岁
I was nine at that time.
慢着 9 9岁
Wait. Nine-nine years old?
我那时对拼图游戏很入迷
I was crazy about puzzles.
我也喜欢您的书
And I like your books.
也许不是"失落的表意文字语言" 而是其他的
Maybe not "Lost language of Ideograms", but the others.
好吧
Okay.
我全看了
I read them all.
古怪的小年轻
A weird kid.
的确如此
I was actually.
我刚刚讲得很大声吗
Did I say that out loud?
是的
You did.
非常抱歉
Very sorry.
兰登教授 您的头疼症状一开始会比较强烈
Professor Langdon, your headaches are going to be intense initially.
您也可能还会有恶心 糊涂 头昏等情况
And you can also expect nausea, confusion and dizziness.
前台来的电话
That was the front desk.
警察来了 要见您
The police are here to see you.
我 为什么
Me, why?
在与他们交流之前 兰登教授 您应该了解一下您的真实情况
Before you talk to them, Professor Langdon, you should know the facts of your case.
您头部的创伤并非事故所致
Your head wound was not caused by an accident.
而是枪击造成的
It was the result of a gunshot.
一枚子弹擦过您头骨顶端 您很可能还狠狠地摔了下来
A bullet grazed the top of your skull and you most likely took a bad fall
这是导致脑震荡的原因
which is what caused the concussion.
如果子弹再往里一英吋
If the bullet had been an inch to the side,
它就真的要命了
it could have killed you.
快点 快点儿
Come on, Come on
这边 这边 快
This way. This way, come on.
出租车
Taxi.
进来
Get in.
啥 你们喝醉了吗
What, are you drunk?
怎么回事
What happened?
快走
Let's go!
加速 开快点
Step on it. Floor it!
- 出了啥事 - 我不知道
- What's going on? - I don't know
接下来会比较疼
This is gonna hurt.
没关系
It's okay. It's okay.
罗伯特
Robert.
寻找 就寻见
Seek and find.
寻找 就必寻见
佛罗伦萨 意大利 凌晨 4:52
Seek and find.
Florence, Italy 4:52 AM
这儿是我的住处
This is my apartment.
你仍在佛罗伦萨
You're still in Florence.
我要打电话叫警察
I'm going to call the police.
等会 那个女警刚刚才试着杀掉咱们
Wait. That policewoman just tried to kill us.
好的
Okay.
那我们打给美国领事馆 如果你没意见的话
We will call the U.S. Consulate instead if you like.
先慢着 让我 ... 让我歇会
Just... wait. Just give me... give me a minute.
- 整理下情况 - 为什么会有人射杀你
- Get a hold on things - Why was someone shooting at you?
我不知道
I don't know.
还有 你进急诊室时
Also, when you came into ER,
你在反覆喃喃些什么
you were mumbling something over and over.
非常抱 ... 非常抱歉
Very sorr... Very sorry.
非常抱歉
Very sorry.
你知道你当时为什么要讲这些吗
Do you have any idea why you would be saying this?
- 不知道 - 为什么有人要射杀你
- No. - Why was someone shooting at you?
你可以继续对我追问这些 女士
You can keep asking me these questions, lady.
但我也不知道答案是什么
But I'm not going to know these answers!
我叫西恩娜
My name is Sienna.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你好
Hello.
Hi.
你刚刚问了很多问题
You just asked a lot of questions.
没错 我感觉我现在非常玻璃心
Yeah, I'm feeling a tad vulnerable right now.
我现在身旁待着一个正被追杀的人
I'm with someone other people want to shoot at!
对不起
I'm sorry.
这些问题很重要
Questions are important.
我希望你能记起来
And I hope you recover.
我可以再要 ... 一杯
Can I ask you for a... cup of a...
那啥 棕色的 热的
What? It's brown and it's... hot.
人们早上喝来补充能量的 呃
People drink it in the morning for energy. Uh...
茶
Tea.
茶 不 另一种
Tea. No. The other one.
- 咖啡 - 咖啡
- Coffee. - Coffee.
我能要一杯咖啡吗
Could I have a cup of coffee?
当然
Sure.
谢谢
Thank you.
你整理得很好
You are very organized.
我喜欢井井有条的样子
I like things tidy.
谢谢你在医院里的帮助
Thank you for helping me in the hospital.
非常勇敢
That was very courageous.
本能反应罢了
It's just reflexes.
"非常抱歉"
"Very sorry".
非常...
Very...
抱歉
sorry
我想我有些幻觉
I feel I'm having visions.
那是因为头部创伤
It's the head trauma.
一段时间内 你会无法依赖自己的意识
You won't be able to trust your own thoughts for a while.
我看见一个瘟疫面具
I saw a plague mask.
有点像中世纪医生 ... 在黑死病肆虐时期的形象
It's the kind the medieval doctors wore in... during the Black death.
你讲过类似的
You said something about that.
你在出租车里讲过 不过大多不连贯
You were talking in the cab it was mostly incoherent but...
但我的确听到"面具"两字
But I did hear the word mask.
还有吗
Anything else?
还有躯体 血液 火焰 ...
The bodies, the blood and fire and...
... 和地狱
... hell.
还有位女士
And there's a woman.
那位女士 她看着 ...
The woman, she seemed...
寻找 就必寻见
Seek and find
呃 看着很吓人
Uh. Well, seemed so dangerous.
不 你肯定有人我们可以联系一下的
No, you got to have somebody we should call.
我有吗 为什么
I do? Why?
我的 ... 我有没有
My wat... Was I wearing
在去医院的时候戴着块手表
my watch when I was brought to the hospital?
没
No.
你没戴表
You weren't wearing a watch.
它对我意义重大 是我父母送的
It's important to me. It was a gift from my parents.
嘿 你该朝前看 忘掉它
Look, you should go ahead and clean up.
你的衣服沾血了 不过我想我有适合你穿的
Your clothes are covered in blood but I think I got something that might fit you.
你穿上后 我们就打电话给警方 行吗
Once you get dressed, we'll call the police, okay?
不 不 领事馆
No. No. The Consulate.
行 领事馆
Right. The Consulate.
咖啡
Coffee.
入读伦敦国王学院的12岁神童
Prodidy, 12, to attend King's College
伊格纳奇奥·布索尼 (昵称"小主教座堂")：我祈祷你一切安好
Ignazio Busoni: I PRAY YOU ARE ALL RIGHT
伊格纳奇奥
Ignazio?
抱歉无法依计划与你会面
I'm sorry I couldn't meet as planned.
他们现在找上我了
Now they're after me too.
我们所窃之物
What we stole
藏于安全之所 本人亦是
... is safely hidden, as am I.
我们所窃之物
"What we stole"?
天堂 25
Paradise Twenty-five.
伊格纳奇奥
Ignazio.
你的东西我都放浴室了
I've left your things in the bathroom.
试试这些
Try these.
这是谁的
Whose are they?
一位朋友的
A friend.
他住这吗
Does he live here?
有时候
Sometimes.
噢 有时候 蛤
Oh. Sometimes, huh.
你有点粗鲁了
You're being rude.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
抱歉 我不是那种人
I'm sorry, I'm not like this.
那可说不准
You kind of are.
我在旧夹克里发现了这个
I found this in my old jacket.
这是生物试管
It's a biotube.
用于运输危险物质
They're used for transporting dangerous substances.
你用来干嘛
What are you doing with it?
我不知道
I have no idea.
这是个高端装置
It's a high end unit.
官方制造的
Government issue.
这儿是指纹识别 万一遗失或被盗后的安保措施
It's called thumbprint recognition.
Security in case it's lost or stolen.
这种管子只能由某位特定人物开启
Tubes like this can only be opened by a specified individual.
这个 人肯定不是我
Well, it sure hell isn't me.
- 那你为什么带着它 - 我不知道
- Then why do you have it? - I don't know.
我去查一下领事馆的号码
I'm getting the number for the Consulate.
请不要 等等
No, please. Wait.
我等过了 这样做不合适
I have waited. This isn't right.
你怎么会有它 你从哪儿弄的
Why do you have it? Where did you get it?
瞧 有个简单的法子
Look, there is a simple way
可以弄清楚它究竟是不是我的
to find out if this thing belongs to me.
我去用拇指打开它 或者尝试失败
Then my thumb will open it or it won't.
打开它 你疯了吗
Open it, are you insane?
如果它是病毒药剂 我打开后它会被释放吗
If it's a viral agent, will it be released if I opened it?
不会
No.
不会的 内部会有一层密封 甚至可能两层
No, there'll be an inner seal maybe even two.
把我自己交给别人之前 我想知道这是啥玩意
Before I put myself in anyone's hands I want to know what this thing is.
嗯 还有我卷进了什么事件里面
Uh, and what I'm involved with.
一切都合情合理 对吗
That make sense, doesn't it?
对的
Yes.
那么 达成一致
So, we agree.
我们把它打开
We're opening it.
好吧 那说明它就是我的
Well, that explains that it is mine.
一个象牙制成的密封圆柱体
This is a cylinder seal made of ivory.
不对
No.
这是骨头
It's bone.
人骨
Human.
三头带角的撒旦 正在吞噬三个人
Three-headed, man eating Satan.
中世纪时的常见形象
A common image from the Middle Ages
这与黑死病密切相连
associated with the Black Plague.
三张血盆大口
The 3 gnashing mouths are symbolic of
正是这瘟疫在人群中肆虐的象征
how effectively the plague ate through the population.
而你却记不起"咖啡"该怎么讲
Yet you can't remember the word for coffee.
它在一定程度上解释了我的幻觉
It explains my visions, sort of.
- 你听见了吗 - 嗯
- Do you hear that? - Mm-mm.
可能是个法拉第指示器
This could be a Faraday pointer.
为 为什么会这样 嗯
So why-why this, huh?
波提切利的画作 (文艺复兴早期的意大利佛罗伦萨画派艺术家)
It's Botticelli.
这是他的"地狱图"
It's his map of hell.
详细描绘了但丁笔下的地狱 (但丁 - 神曲·地狱篇)
He painted it as an illustration of Dante's Inferno.
年轻的时候我学习过但丁的作品
I studied Dante when I was younger.
也许是在幼儿园里
Probably in kindergarden.
当时挺着迷的
I was a bit obsessed.
但丁定义了现代社会中的地狱概念
Dante defined our modern conception of hell.
我们对地狱的看法700年前就定型了
Our vision of it hasn't changed since he defined it 700 years ago.
波提切利画了出来 但 ... 但丁是众所周知的缔造者
Botticelli drew it but... Dante created hell as we know it.
这也是我的幻觉所见
This is what I have been seeing.
酷刑拷问 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的献诈者)
Torment.
罪孽亡魂 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的挑拨离间者)
Sinners.
贩子被打上烙印 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的神棍)
Branding the mongers.
说谎者全身发疹 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的作伪者)
Liars, covered with rashes.
预言者头部倒反 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的占卜者)
Soothsayers with their heads turned backwards.
- 蛇 - 对偷窃的刑罚 (图为地狱第八层：欺诈的盗贼)
- Serpents. - The punishment for thievery.
受难吧 罪人们 为汝之孽付出代价
Suffer, you sinners. Pay for your sins.
那么你对为何拥有此物一无所知
So you have no idea why you have this?
我想现在或许该联系领事馆了
I think maybe we call the consulate now.
对
Right.
兰登教授
Professor Langdon?
你好 是的 是我
Hello, yes. Speaking.
谢天谢地你还活着 我们一直在找你
Thank heavens you're alive. We've been looking for you.
是吗
You have?
你还带着吗
Are you still in possession?
兰登先生 管子还在吗
Mr. Langdon, do you have the tube?
- 是的 - 你的位置是
- Yes. - Where are you located?
教授 我们找不着你 就无法帮你
Professor, we can't help you if we can't find you.
如果那是领事馆 他们又如何知情
If that's the consulate, how do they know?
因为他们本就知道
Because they know.
怎么办
What do we do?
告诉他们你在那儿
Tell them you're over there.
- 你好 - 教授 刚才断线了
- Hello. - Professor, we were cut off.
是的 抱歉
Yes, sorry.
你在哪儿
Where are you located?
我在一家旅馆里 佛罗伦萨家庭旅馆
I'm at a hotel, Pensione la Fiorentina.
待在房间里 我们的人马上就到
Stay in your room. We're sending someone now.
我在这等着 39号房
I'll wait here, room 39.
好的 我们就等着 看他们派谁来
Okay. We wait and see who they send.
世界卫生组织 流动指挥车
清晨 6:37
兰登通过佛罗伦萨的一个未加密IP登录了邮箱帐号
Langdon accessed his email account from an unmasked IP address here in Florence
- 什么时候 - 7分钟前
- When? - 7 minutes ago.
维亚多乐罗莎大道12号3C公寓
Via Dolorosa, number 12, apartment 3C.
维亚多乐罗莎大道 要多久
Via Dolorosa, how long?
12分钟
12 minutes.
行动 拿回指示器 还有兰登
Go! I want that pointer back and I want Langdon.
无论如何 把他抓回来
Whatever it takes, let's get him.
走 走 走 走 就现在
Go, go, go, go, now!
看这个 好奇怪
Look at this. This is odd.
这块区域是但丁的地狱第八层
This area here is Dante's 8th level of hell.
叫Malebolge 意为邪恶之囊
It's called the Malebolge, means evil ditches.
一共有十种罪恶
There's ten.
这儿的字母"R" 原画中并没有
This letter "R" here, is not in the original painting.
是后加的
It's been added.
还有一个
There's another one.
- 哪里 - 有个"E"
- Where? - An "E".
被恶魔鞭笞的诱奸者
On seducers whipped by demons.
- 面颊上有个"C"的人 - 是污吏
- There's a "C" on the cheek of a... - A grafter.
- 贪污犯 - 困在满池沸腾沥青中的骗子
- ... a grafter. - A conman trapped in a pool of boiling tar.
- "V" "R" - 啊 那儿
- A "V", "R".
- Ah, there.
- "T" - 那儿 那儿 "A"
- "T". - There, there, "A".
那是什么
What is that.
一段文字 那是英文吗
That's text. Is that in English?
唯有透过死亡之眼 才能瞥见真相
THE TRUTH CAN BE GLIMPSED ONLY THROUGH THE EYES OF DEATH.
佐布里斯特
ZOBRIST.
贝特朗·佐布里斯特
Bertrand Zobrist.
- 美国的亿万富翁 那一定很棒 - 蛤
- American billionaire, that must be nice. - Hm.
生物工程师
Bioengineer
因激进观点而声名狼藉
Notorious for radical views.
他在这儿
Here he is.
人类经历了10万年
It took the earth's population a hundred thousand years
才繁衍出10亿人口
to reach a billion people.
在随后的100年 人口增长到20亿
And then just a hundred more to reach two billion.
再翻一番只花了50年 70年代人口40亿
And only fifty years to double again to four billion people in 1970.
现在 我们快有80亿了
We're nearly at eight billion now.
巴特利特以烧杯为例 (巴特利特：英国化学家)
Bartlett used the example of a beaker.
内有一个细菌细胞
With a single bacterium.
每分钟分裂一次 数目翻倍
One that divides and doubles every minute.
如果在11点整将第一个细菌细胞置于杯中
If you placed the first bacterium into the beaker at 11 o'clock.
12点整时杯就全满了
and it's completely full by 12.
在何时烧杯还是半满的呢
At what time is the beaker still only half full?
11:59
那就是现在的我们
That's what time it is for us.
未来40年内 会有320亿人口 在生死线上挣扎
In 40 years, 32 billion people... will fight to survive.
还没失败
No fail.
距离午夜 我们还差一分钟
We're a minute to midnight.
每一次全球性的瘟疫灾难都可以被归咎于人口的过剩
Every single global ill that plagues the Earth can be traced back to human overpopulation.
而严肃的生育控制手段却毫无施行可能
But serious birth control measures they don't stand a chance.
耸人听闻 违背个人权利
Outrageous! Violation of my rights!
侵犯个人隐私 别来好为人师
Invasion of my privacy! Don't tell me what to do!
然而 我们仍在侵略自然环境
But still we keep attacking our own environment!
地球历史上已经有过5次物种大灭绝
They have been 5 major extinctions in the earth's history.
我们若不立即采取大胆行动
Unless we take bold immediate action
第六次就会轮到我们头上
the sixth extinction will be our own.
距离午夜 我们还差一分钟
We're a minute to midnight.
看起来他有挺多拥护者
Looks like he's got a lot of followers.
嗯 来自全球各地 五湖四海
Yeah, from all over the world.
他挺令人信服的
He is compelling.
在佐布里斯特消失的两年时间里 部分当局人员担心
The 2 year disappearance during which some authorities feared Zobrist
他可能研发了一种有害于免疫能力底下群体的病毒病原体
may have designed an opportunistic viral pathogen.
他制造了一种瘟疫病毒
He created a plague.
但 为什么是但丁
But, why Dante?
为什么是这幅"地狱图"
Why this map of hell?
这是拼图游戏 或者挑战吗
Is this supposed to be a puzzle or a challenge?
也可能是遗书
Or a suicide note.
3天前他自杀了
He killed himself 3 days ago.
等级
The levels.
罪恶等级是乱序的 这是困扰我的地方
The levels are out of order, that's what's been bothering me.
地狱这一层的次序被重新分布了
This circles of hell had been rearranged.
跟医院的女子是同一人
It's the same woman from the hospital.
我们不能待在这 肯定不能相信领事馆了
We can't stay here. We certainly can't trust the Consulate.
字母像布置时那样被加密 也不对
The letters are encrypted as committers, that's not right.
如果病毒真的存在 你知道有多少政府想要弄到手吗
If the plague exist, do you know how many governments would want it?
神棍 猜不出
Clerical profiteers, not there.
- 他们都会做些什么来得到这些 - 挑拨离间者 不是
- What they would do to get it. - Someone who discord dead, no.
生化武器
A biological weapon.
这些字母
The letters.
他把每种罪行都加上了字母 然后打乱次序
He has assigned a letter to each sin and then changed their order.
他设了一个字谜
He's made an anagram.
对了 字谜
Yes. Anagram.
走 我知道另一条路能出去
Let's go. I know another way out.
如果你带了手机 最好留在这儿
If you have phoned, best leave it here.
可能会被追踪
They might track it.
手机 衣服都不是我自个的
The phone? I'm not even wearing my own clothes.
很好 走吧
Good. Let's go.
罗伯特·兰登 世界卫生组织
Robert Langdon! World Health Organization! (WHO)
V, R, O.
我得重排这些字母 Over Code
I got to rearrange these letters, CATROVACER.
Covered Cat
天 这种东西我以前挺上手的
God. I used to be good at this.
Cerca trova.
意大利语 意为"寻找"和"发现"
It's Italian. It means "seek" and "find".
Cerca trova 好的
Cerca trova. Yes!
我知道我为什么会在佛罗伦萨了
I know why I am in Florence.
世界卫生组织已经抵达 待命
World Health Organization has landed, standby.
注意
Be advised.
来自巴黎的布沙尔探员已经到场
Agent Bouchard, from the Paris office is already here.
世界卫生组织 告诉我最新情况
W.H.O, Bring me up to speed.
布沙尔已经上去了
Bouchard is up there now.
- 我们去哪 - 旧宫 波波利花园附近
- Where are we going? - The Palazzo Vecchio, near the Boboli Gardens.
没有发现他
There's no sign of him.
布沙尔说兰登已经走了 指示器也不在
Bouchard says Langdon is gone and so is the pointer.
这可不行
Well, I need better.
你 你 你们全部都要表现得更好
I need better from you, from you, from all of us.
更像样
Better!
还要更迅速 更敏捷 别相信任何人
Work faster. Work smarter. Don't trust anyone.
大家加油吧
Let's do that.
- 去吧 - 是
- Let's go. - Yes.
情报看样子已经没用了
The information seems to be obsolete.
- 不要透露给秘书长 明白吗 - 明白
- Do not say anything to the secretary general. - OK
- 身份 - 瓦任莎
- Identification. - Vayentha.
- 继续 - 我要跟教务长通话
- Go ahead. - I need to speak to the provost.
稍等
Hold on.
亚得里亚海 (意大利东部地中海水域) 清晨 7:12
游艇"门达西乌姆号"
Adriatic Sea 7:12 AM
The Mendacium.
那么 WHO在追踪兰登这事上先你一步 瓦任莎
So, the WHO beat you to Mr. Langdon, Vayentha.
教务长可不喜欢这样
The provost isn't going to like that.
我知道 他想要清掉我了
I know. He's going to want to liquidate.
告诉他这儿不是柏林
Tell him this isn't Berlin.
他敢试 我就找上门
He tries anything and I will find him.
一小时内再试一遍 然后联系我们
Try to reacquire and make contact in 60 minutes.
你有没有在听 我不是一次性用品
Did you hear me? I am not disposable.
瓦任莎 抢先将法拉第指示器弄到手
Vayentha, get the Faraday pointer before the government does.
靠
Shit.
- 西姆斯先生 - 嗯
- Mr. Sims. - Mm.
事情出了点偏差
There's been a deviation.
听到这个真遗憾
Sorry to hear that.
- 什么行动 - 佛罗伦萨
- What operation? - Florence.
我们的新外勤似乎有点随性乱来了
Our new players seemed to have gone off script.
真够业余
How unprofessional.
现在WHO已经取代了我们的位置
And now the WHO has overtaken our position.
告诉瓦任莎 如果她还在乎这份工作
Tell Vayentha, if she values her position
她就该除掉兰登
she will remove Langdon.
毁尸灭迹
Body not found.
或者再妙点 拦路抢劫
Or better yet, a mugging gone awry.
来上一刀 我觉得 现金劫走 钱包留下
A blade, I think. Cash gone, wallet remains.
赶紧确认下 然后继续 继续 继续
Let's have a quick identification and move on. Move on, move on.
兰登教授已经脱离监视了
Professor Langdon is out of frame.
- 还带着管子吗 - 是的
- And in possession of the tube? - Yes.
他带着法拉第指示器
He has the Faraday pointer.
之前盯的那么紧
He was such a good frame.
- 瓦任莎的情况如何 - 无恙 但很焦虑
- What is Vayentha's condition? - Intact but anxious.
那也正常
She should be.
这位委托人究竟都让我们做了些什么
What in god's name has this client gotten us into?
不不不 只是个 ... 比方
No, no, no. This is uh... rhetorical.
我们什么时候准备好发布委托人的视频
When are we due to release the client's video?
视频刚到这
It just arrived.
他的指示是24小时内上传
His instructions were to upload it in 24 hours.
我现在想看一下
I want to look at it now.
但 委托人 佐布里斯特
But, the client, Mr. Zobrist.
委托人 委托人已经死了 我要看视频
The client, the client is dead. I want to see the video.
这是违约行为
That's a violation of our protocols.
我们不是政府 只是负责办事
We're not the government. We get things done.
阿博加斯特先生
Mr. Arbogast.
能够令我们在工作中得心应手的首要因素
Chief among the attributes that makes us so very good at our job
正是世人对我们存在的一无所知
is that as far as the world is concerned, we don't exist.
倘若这段视频暗示或甚至提及到我们
If this video implicates or even mentions us in anyway,
我就会基于客户权益考虑而中止其发布
I want to stop it's release. For the benefit of all our clients.
你要求过在流程操作中要避免异常事况 就这些
You asked me to avoid abnormalities in procedure, that's all.
如果佐布里斯特先生当初只是在假装正常交易 怎么办
What about Mr. Zobrist has ever remotely resembled normal.
- 那 我... - 也只是个比方
- Well, I... - Also rhetorical.
把视频带过来
Bring me the video.
在旧宫(维奇奥宫)的五百人大厅内 有一副著名壁画
马基雅维利大道 佛罗伦萨 意大利 上午 8:36
In the Vecchio's Hall of the Five Hundred, there's a famous mural,
Viale Machiavelli, Florence, Italy 8:36 AM
乔治奥·瓦萨里的"马西阿诺之战"
Giorgio Vasari's Battle of Marciano.
在壁画顶部附近 有一段密文
Near the top of the mural is a coded message
这也是艺术界中最著名的未解之谜
which is one the art world's most famous puzzles.
密文是什么
And what's the message?
Cerca trova.
寻找 就寻见
Seek and find.
在医院里 我一直念叨说我很抱歉
At the hospital, I kept saying I was sorry.
很抱歉 一遍又一遍
Very sorry, over and over.
好吧 也许那不是我的本意
Well, maybe that's not what I meant.
画家的名字 瓦萨里 我可能讲的是"瓦萨里"
The name of the artist, Vasari. I could have been saying Vasari.
很棒啊 感觉你清醒多了
That's good. You seem clearer.
- 是的 - 你的中间名叫什么
- I am. - What's your middle name?
呃 我挺清醒的
Well, I am.
嗯哼
Mm-hm.
佐布里斯特死了 但若病毒真的存在
Zobrist is dead but if his plague is real...
那这幅"地狱图" 就是他留给某人找到它的线索
Then this map is a trail he has left so someone can find it.
谁
Who?
嗯 跟他立场一致的人
Well, someone who believes the same as he does.
那就是你带着它的原因
And that's why you have it.
但我印象中从未见过他
Well, I don't remember ever meeting Zobrist.
你不记得的事情可多了
There's a lot you don't remember.
也许他们 也许他们之前找到你
Maybe they- Maybe they came to you.
征求过你的指引
Wanted your help with the path.
- 就因为我做过但丁的讲座 - 正是如此
- Because I lectured on Dante? - Exactly.
他们向你展示法拉第指示器 试着说服你支持那些主张
They showed you this Faraday pointer, tried to convince you of their cause.
- 大屠杀 - 你说过他挺令人信服的
- Mass murder? - You said you found him compelling.
那是指观点
His argument!
口才
His rhetoric.
绝非这些计划 佐布里斯特心理上有问题
Not his plan! Zobrist is a psychopath.
好吧 或许他们耍了你
Well, maybe they tricked you.
其实给了 ... 你认识的人
Sent... someone you knew.
离午夜还差一分钟
It's a minute to midnight.
- 那是对付咱们的吗 - 常理来看是的
- Is that for us? - Logic would suggest.
该死
Damn it!
这儿 快 跟上我
Here, come on. Follow me.
我们可以穿过花园到那儿
We could get there through the garden.
好的 旧宫在这边
Okay, the- the Palazzo Vecchio is this way.
过去一小时内 我们标记了她用信用卡购买的汽车
We just flagged the car charged to her credit card within the past hour.
安托万 你跟警方交涉了么
Antoine, did you talk to the police?
那边有见过咱们的警察
There are people who have seen me.
请跟当地警方合作
Please cooperate with local police officially.
WHO将负责监督波波利花园的搜查工作
W.H.O. will take charge overseeing the search at the Boboli Gardens.
把搜查犬调过来
Call in the search dogs.
我在警局里接到电话 前来支援你
I got called out from the police station to support you.
波波利花园 上午 8:42
Boboli Gardens 8:42 AM
我需要更多帮手
I need more people.
报告电台 发现嫌犯
Radio in, suspects found.
该死的 四组 检查北边
Damn it! Delta, check the north perimeter.
这儿下去有扇灰色的小门
There's a small gray door down here.
直通瓦萨里长廊
It will take us into the Vasari corridor.
穿过维奇奥桥 就进到了宫里
Right across the Ponte Vecchio, and into the Palazzo.
- 门在那 看 - 哦
- That's the door, see. - Yeah.
就现在
Now!
花园是不是被墙整个围住的
Is the garden completely walled.
四面全封闭
On all sides.
唯一的出口要穿过北面的碧提宫
The only exits are through the Palazzo Pitti, on the north side,
或者通过东西两侧接待游客的大门
and through the visitors gates on the east and west sides.
没有别的出路了
No other way out?
如果瓦萨里长廊大门也算的话
I suppose if you count the Vasari gate.
不过那门很老 鲜有人知
But it's ancient, no one knows about that.
兰登知道
Langdon does.
教授现在是个麻烦了 瓦任莎
The Professor has become a liability, Vayentha.
教务长已经发布了诛杀令 除掉兰登
The provost has issued a kill order. Eliminate Langdon.
如若失败 你要负责 我说得够清楚了吗
Fail, and you will be held accountable. Am I making myself clear?
明白了 长官
Copy that, sir.
旧宫五百人大厅 早上 9:13
那儿
There.
瓦萨里的壁画 马西阿诺之战
That's the Vasari fresco, The Battle of Marciano.
那儿 那儿 看 看 看 看
There. There. Look. Look, look, look.
好的 看那两栋农舍 壁画中间往上
Okay, see the 2 farmhouses, dead center up high,
往4点钟方向下移一点
come down to it's 4 o'clock,
你就看到一小面绿色战旗
and you'll see a small green flag.
- Cerca trova - 对
- Cerca trova. - Yeah.
寻找 就寻见
Seek and find.
咱们看到了 找到了
We sought it and we found it.
那么 现在做什么
So, now what?
佐布里斯特加到画里的话
The words Zobrist added to the painting.
唯有透过死亡之眼 才能瞥见真相
The truth can be glimpsed only through the eyes of death.
死亡之眼
Eyes of death.
谁的眼睛
Whose's eyes?
我是不是被注射了什么东西
Was I given an injection?
什么时候
When?
- 医院里面 颈动脉注射 - 没有
- At the hospital, with a hypertenol? - No.
没有 你是插管输液治疗 只有静脉滴注
No, you were intubated. Anything you got came through the IV.
不在医院里
Not at the hospital.
我当时身着正装 在车厢后座上
I was fully dress. I was in the back of some car...
大概是过去两天里的某个时候
at some point in the last 2 days.
有东西注入了我的血液里
And something was injected into my bloodstream.
然后现在我开始外现临床病状
and now I'm showing signs of an illness
会不会是...
What if...?
会是什么
What if what?
西恩娜 我会不会就是携带者
Sienna, what if I'm the carrier?
你看
Look.
如果你携带了 那我也会被感染
If you've got it then I've got it too.
还有我们接触过的每个人同样如此 都会死掉
And everyone we've come into contact with has it and will likely die.
但如果并非如此
But if you don't.
如果 如果他们注射的是药剂或致幻剂 或者别的东西
If-If they gave you an anotic or a hallucinogen or anything else.
那么我们仍有机会挽救这半个世界
Then we still have a chance to save half the world.
值得一试 不是么
It's worth a try, isn't it?
教授
Professor.
啊 真是你 你怎么这么快就回来了
Ah, it is you. Why are you back so soon?
我不知道她是谁
I have no idea who this woman is.
你这身行头我差点没认出来 在逛街吗
I almost didn't recognize you in that suit. You've been shopping?
教授 你的头被撞了
Professor, you bumped your head.
是的 洗澡的时候 暴跌一跤
In the shower, yes. It's quite a tumble.
- 哎呀 - 嗯
- Ayes. - Yeah.
打扰一下 这位是西恩娜 我的侄女
I'm sorry. This is Sienna, my niece.
你人在意大利呢 教授 不必提这个
You're in Italy, Professor, you don't have to say 'niece'.
- 不是 不是的 - 不是的 他没有
- No. No. - No, he's not.
你好 玛塔·阿尔瓦雷兹 很高兴见到你
Hello. Marta Alvarez. Pleasure to meet you.
伊格纳奇奥(小主教座堂)也跟你一块来了吗
Is Ignazio with you again?
- 伊格纳奇奥 - 对
- Ignazio? - Yeah.
伊格纳奇奥今早没能成行
Ignazio couldn't make it this morning.
很抱歉打搅你一下 玛塔 不过
I'm sorry to bother you, Marta. But...
我想你大概能想到我为什么会在这里 又一次
I can imagine you know why I'm back. Again.
真的吗
Really?
旧宫里头这么多的珍宝
Of all the treasures in the Palazzo.
昨天晚上他跟小主教座堂在那上面待了将近一个钟头
He and il Duomino spent almost an hour with it up there last night.
真的 非同寻常
It's-It's so morbid.
哪里哪里 这很正常
No. No. It's cool.
好了 来吧 我来带路
Alright, come on. I'm headed up that way.
他真是足智多谋的一个能人
He's an extremely resourceful man.
我也对你说过这话 布沙尔先生
I was told you were as well, Mr. Bouchard.
那么 告诉我
So. Tell me.
你觉得他在干嘛
What do you think he's doing?
你觉得你在干嘛
What you think you doing?
我把指示器带给你 现在它没了
I brought you the pointer and now it's gone.
- 你弄丢了 - 我们在街上跟丢了他
- You have a leak. - We losed him in the street.
在医生的住处又重新发现了
Reacquired him at the doctor's apartment.
有大家支持 我还能掌控
I can handle with some ground.
- 我们不需要你帮忙 - 如果他受伤了
- We don't need your help. - What if he's injured.
头部受创
A head wound.
什么意思 你认为他糊涂了
What? You think he's confused.
- 他不知道他在干嘛吗 - 有可能
- He doesn't know what he's doing? - It's possible.
他晚上失踪前进展到了哪里
How far did he get the night before he disappeared?
五百人大厅
To the Hall of Five Hundred.
那我们就不追了
So let's stop chasing him,
提前守着他
anticipate him instead.
嘿 朋友 还请悠着点
Whoa, inspector. Not so fast, please.
我快燃起来了
I'm about to burst.
这么浪漫的一天 他却带你来欣赏死亡面具
Such a romantic date he takes you on. To see a death mask.
是的 在16世纪 它们相当普遍
Yeah, they were common practice in the 1500s.
实质上就是某个人面部的石膏模型
It's essentially just a plaster cast of someone's face,
在其死后不久套模浇注的
made a few moments after that person dies.
"透过死亡之眼"
"Through the eyes of death."
这幅面具的模型 是一位诗人
The person who was used for this mask, the poet,
叫但丁
Dante.
我想这是一个浪漫的故事
It is a romantic story I supposed.
但丁热爱这座城市 他在当时很显赫 又有影响力 但
Dante loved Florence, he was prominent and powerful. But...
在政治权力更迭后 他被罢黜流放
The political winds changed and he was exiled.
人们威胁他 若胆敢回来 就火刑伺候
They threatened to burn him at the stake if he ever returned.
实际上 有人认为对但丁的放逐 是面具看着如此悲恸的原因
Actually, some people say Dante's exile is the reason his death mask looks so sad.
不 不对 那是因为比阿特丽斯的原因 ("神曲"中的人物)
No. No. It was because of Beatrice.
但丁只从远处见过她 但她却被其终生迷恋
Dante only knew her from afar but he was obsessed with her his entire life.
你的侄女很浪漫呢 教授
Your niece is a romantic, Professor.
人们认为 但丁所撰的穿越地狱之行 实际上是为了找到她
They say Dante wrote in fact about his journey out of hell to reach her.
但他没能成功
But he never made it.
她已嫁给另主
She married someone else.
这事常常发生
That happens.
有吗
Does it?
谁撇下了谁
Who left who?
有些东西 若你不加以照料 就会难以为继
Things fall apart if you don't look after them.
噢 馆方要求 参观时你们只能站在立柱外
Oh. We ask that you stay behind the stanchions. Please.
谢谢
Thank you.
来得很巧 教授 我们刚刚开门
Good timing, Professor. We've only just opened.
玛塔...
Marta...
在
Yes?
那儿 那是我们
There. That's us.
那是伊格纳奇奥·布索尼 ("小主教座堂")
That's Ignazio Busoni.
我们相识多年
I've known him for years.
他是研究但丁的学者
He's the Dante scholar.
面具的主人坚持要求参观者要站在立柱之外
The mask's owner insists on the stanchions to keep people back.
未经许可 工作人员也不能打开展柜
He doesn't even permit staff to open the case without him present.
所以面具不是博物馆所有
So the mask is not owned by the museum?
不是 有位私人收藏家从我们手里买下了
No. A private collector bought it from us,
并允许我们做永久性展览
and allows us to display it in perpetuity.
这是筹集经费的惯常做法
It's a common practice, to raise funds.
他是何许人也
Who is the collector?
贝特朗·佐布里斯特 那位亿万富翁
Bertram Zobrist, the billionaire.
他的观点很古怪 但其自杀之事仍旧令人遗憾
His ideas were quite eccentric, but still it's such a shame what happened.
那就是我接电话的时候了
That's when I got the call.
喔
Oh.
教授 我 我不知道该作何感想
Professor, I... I don't know what to think!
我很震惊
I am appalled!
- 教授 - 兰登教授
- Professor. - Professor Langdon.
瞧 这事情肯定有个解释
Look. There's an explanation for all this.
警察来了 警铃响了
The police came and the alarm went off.
这些都是什么人
Who are they?
他们都是特工人员
They're government agents.
你有客人了
You have an intruder.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
玛塔 别让他俩跑了
Marta, don't let them go.
你不能带枪进这来
You can not bring a gun here.
教授
Professor.
教授 我非常尊敬您 但我不明白
Professor, I very much respect you but I do not understand.
- 请坐 我会解释 - 你为什么做这事
- Please sit down. I'm going to explain this. - Why you have done this?
- 那可不行 - 玛塔 我不知道面具在哪儿
- This is not okay. - Marta, I do not know where the mask is.
但我会竭尽全力找到它 还给你们
But I will do everything I can to find it and return it to you.
教授 你在干嘛 教授 求你 不要
Professor, what are you doing? Professor, please. No.
教授 回来 别这样
Professor, come back. Don't do that.
教授 请不要
Professor, please don't.
- 嘿 嘿 - 教授
- Hey. Hey. - Professor.
- 你别跟着就好 - 求你了 别这样
- Just don't follow us. - Please, don't do this.
教授
Professor!
咱们偷偷找条路子离开这儿
Let's just calmly find a way out of here.
你为什么不告诉我伊格纳奇奥的事情
Why didn't you tell me about Ignazio?
如果你知道我是个贼 你还会帮我吗
Would you help me if you knew I was a thief?
你向我求助的时候撒了谎
You lied to me when you asked for my help.
对 严格说来 我有所保留
Well technically, I withheld.
如果我真的拿了那副面具...
If I really took that mask...
你的确拿了 我刚刚才看到
You did take the mask, I just saw you.
这不是你的问题 你不必跟着
This is not your problem. You don't have to stay.
我当然要陪着 人类正面临生死存亡
Of course, I do. Human lives are at stake.
我只想知道我没站错队
I just want to know that I'm on the right side.
你没有
You are.
我发誓
I swear.
好的
Good.
现在咱们去找到要找的东西
Now let's find what we're looking for.
打给伊格纳奇奥 问他面具藏哪儿了
Call this Ignazio, and ask him where he hid the mask.
伊格纳奇奥失踪了 不知藏身何处
Ignazio's disappeared. He had gone into hiding.
他说过
He said.
别人也在追着他 但他留了条线索
They were chasing him too but he left a clue.
一封邮件 "天堂 25"
An email, "Paradise Twenty-five".
指的是但丁"神曲"中的天堂篇第25诗章 不过
That's a reference to Dante's Divine Comedy. "Canto XXV." But...
- 我现在需要那本书 - 一本书
- I need a copy of the book. - A copy of the book.
真荒诞 我会用谷歌
That's quaint. I use Google.
他们正在关闭博物馆 只开放主出口
They're closing down the museum, only the main exit is going to be open.
那我们就穿过亚美尼亚
Well, then we'll go through Armenia.
...从正门有序离开
...Go out to the front door in an orderly manner.
现已封锁全部出口
All exit doors are now sealed.
这是唯一的进出通道
This is the only way in or out.
有没有隐藏的出口 隧道 隐门之类的
What about hidden exits? Tunnels, concealed doorways?
这地方700年了 先生 这类玩意很多
It's a 700 year old Palazzo, Signore, there are a number of them.
带我看看
Show me.
亚美尼亚
ARMENIA
教授 真是刮目相看
Professor. How worldly.
旧宫的秘密之一
Secrets of the Palazzo Invisibile.
这段路很赞 改天你也试试
It's a great tour, you should take it sometime.
我们在这儿暂时安全了
We should be safe here for a minute.
进去
Go.
"到那时 我将带着另一个声音 另一身羊毛..."
"By then with other voice, with other fleece..."
"我将作为诗人回归 并且
在我的洗礼盆中接受那花冠..."
"I shall return as poet and put on,
at my baptismal font, the laurel crown..."
洗礼盆
Baptismal font.
圣母百花大教堂 但丁受洗之地
(译注: Il Duomo实指佛罗伦萨主教座堂广场建筑群 包括圣母百花大教堂 圣若望洗礼堂 乔托钟楼等)
Il Duomo. The Cathedral where Dante was baptized.
也是伊格纳奇奥工作的地方 他把面具藏在那了
That's where Ignazio works. That's where he hid the mask.
不在这儿
It is not here.
他们会认为我们正前往出口
They're going to think we're heading down to the exit.
那么我们往上走
Then we go up.
好的
Alright.
我们正在五百人大厅上面
We're right above the Hall of Five Hundred.
另一头有道楼梯 直通大街
There's a stairway leading down to the street on the other side.
那么
So.
一次迈一步
One step at a time.
行吗
Okay?
你恐高不
Are you afraid of heights?
有点儿
A little.
我倒是有点儿幽闭恐惧症
I'm uncomfortable in tight spaces.
那么 别往下看
So, don't look down.
或者就往下看 我记不得了
Or do. I can never remember which.
没那么难
It's not that hard.
来吧 走
Come on, go.
西恩娜
Sienna!
你还好吗
Are you alright?
- 你还好吗 - 还好
- You okay? - Yeah.
好的 只要... 慢慢去到那边横梁上
Alright, just... crawl along that beam there.
我在另一边跟你碰头 楼梯附近
And I'll meet you on the far side, by the ladder.
长官
Sir.
调派六个人到这来 不用戒备了
Give me a six men stationed here. Safeties off.
你现在变蠢了 兰登教授
You're being stupid now, Professor Langdon!
走 走 离开这儿 走
Go. Go. Get out of here, go!
他们一度需要你 但如今心意已改
They needed you but now they changed their minds.
把人都赶走 大家都离开 清空现场
Get these people out. Everyone out, clear the room.
把它给我
Give me that.
那些门 这儿
These doors, here.
- 东面 他们去那了 - 收到
- Eastern side. That's where they're headed. - Okay.
走 行动 快点
Go, move. Quickly!
布沙尔 布沙尔探员 回话
Bouchard. Agent Bouchard, come in.
你在哪儿 布沙尔探员 回话
What is your location? Agent Bouchard, come in.
重生
REBIRTH
寄来视频的信封上也有这个词
That same word is on the envelope the video arrived in,
上面还有一个日期 是明天
along with the date. The date is tomorrow.
谢谢 这些我知道
Well, thank you, that was not lost on me.
地狱中最黑暗的地方 是为那些
The darkest places in hell are reserved for those
在道德危机时刻皂白不辨的人而准备的
who refuse to act in time of moral crisis.
但丁的地狱并非虚构 它是预言
Dante's hell isn't fiction anymore, it's prophecy.
我们已经在这个星球上打造了人间地狱
We have created our own hell on earth.
天呐
Oh my.
警告已然很明显 对策却被忽略了
The warnings have been obvious, the solutions ignored.
因此 我采取了行动
So, I took action.
如果你看到了这则视频 就意味着地狱病毒
If you are watching this, it means the Inferno virus was released
已在昨晚午夜被释放
last night at midnight, and...
现在早就传遍了全球各个角落
it's now being carried to every corner of the Earth.
天呐
Oh my.
在释放后的6天内 病毒会不断增殖 (译注: 上帝创造天地用时6天)
Within 6 days of it's released, the virus will replicate itself.
地球上的全体人类数量
And every man, woman and child on Earth expect the current...
将会随机减半
the current population to be culled by half.
幸存者则将见证
The survivors will witness
这个星球上前所未有的恐怖
horrors... unknown to this planet.
但我想让大家知道原由
But I want them to know why.
这就是吾之所为 这就是吾之救赎
That this was our doing and this is our salvation.
现在时候已到
Now is the time.
今天是...
Today is...
后面还有
There's more.
我相信我已经明白了视频主旨
I believe I've got the gist.
很明显过去数年以来
It appears our organization has spent
我们在跟一个试图通过自行研发的致命病毒
the last several years in the employ of a madman
来发动人口大屠杀的疯子在打交道
who now intends to commit a mass murder using a deadly plague of his own creation
在接下来24小时的某一刻 ... 抱歉
in some point in the next 24... Sorry.
不到12小时了
Less than 12 hours.
那么 咱们尽吾所能 不要再
So, let's do our level best not to fuck things up
把事儿进一步搞砸了 好吗
any worse than we already have, shall we?
没了法拉第指示器 没人能找到病毒
Without the Faraday pointer, no one can find the virus.
兰登教授现在在哪
Where is Professor Langdon now?
他之前跟布鲁克斯医生在波波利花园 但情报似乎断了
He was with Dr. Brooks in the Boboli Gardens but we seemed to have lost visual.
我们恐怕也有很久没有联系上瓦任莎了
And I'm afraid we have no contact from Vayentha.
知道了
I see.
我亲自去佛罗伦萨
I'm going to Florence myself.
给她做传染性检查 把这里隔离起来
Test her for signs of contagion and quarantine this place.
如果不尽快找到兰登
If we don't find Langdon very soon,
我们很快就会看到更多死尸
we are going to be looking at a great many more dead bodies.
你还好吗
Are you alright?
虚弱
It's weakness.
只是虚弱 该死的
Just weakness, god damn it.
我们歇一会儿
We'll just take a moment.
你见到她掉下去了吗
Did you see her down there?
是的
Yes.
自打我11岁开始 全部所做所学
Everything I've done, every bit of work and studies since I was eleven
就是去救死扶伤 而不是置人死地
is to stop death, not cause it.
那只是自卫 有人要刺杀咱们
It was self defense. Someone was trying to kill us.
我不知道能不能跟下去了
I don't know if I can finish this.
你不能的话 我完全理解
I understand if you can't.
看 佐布里斯特才是谋杀犯 不是你
Look, Zobrist is the murderer, not you.
你救了我
You saved me.
你本不必采取行动的
You don't have to take another step.
嗯 说的没错
Yeah, you're right.
我做了应该做的 若有必要 我还会再来一遍
I did what was necessary and I'll do it again if I need to.
我祈愿这是最后一次
I pray that you don't.
看样子已经关门在搞维修了
Looks like it's close for repairs.
好的 这边
Okay, this way.
圣若望洗礼堂
那儿
There.
洗礼盆
The baptismal font.
又是但丁
Dante again.
总是但丁 为什么是但丁
Always Dante, why Dante?
- 丙烯底涂料 - 你指颜料吗
- Acrylic gesso. - You mean paint.
水性颜料
Water soluble paint.
闻着像是落水狗
Smells like a wet dog.
看那 有笔迹
Look at that. There's a writing.
"寻找那位欺诈的威尼斯总督
"Seek the treacherous Doge of Venice,
- 他曾切断马匹之头" - 威尼斯
- who severed the heads from horses." - Venice.
但丁在那儿身染虐疾 最终客死异乡
Where Dante was infected with the disease that killed him.
"跪在金碧辉煌的神圣智慧博学园内
"Kneel within the gilded museum of holy wisdom,
聆听小溪的流水之声"
and listen for the sounds of trickling water."
"下到水下宫殿深处
"Follow deep into the sunken palace,
- 冥府怪物就在此间等待" - 说的是病毒
- where the chthonic monster waits." - The plague itself.
水面以下
Underwater.
"淹没在血红的水下
"Submerged in the blood-red waters of
- 那里的泻湖不会倒映群星" - 教授
- of the lagoon that reflects no stars." - Professor.
请问你能告诉我你到底在搞什么鬼吗
Could you please tell me what the hell you are doing?
为什么你还不来帮忙
Why haven't you called in?
你是谁
Who are you?
克里斯托夫·布沙尔 世界卫生组织
Christoph Bouchard, from the World Health Organization.
- 我们见过的 - 我们见过
- We've met. - We've met?
你真的不记得了么 才过了两天
You really don't remember? It was just 2 days ago.
他头部受伤 这是副作用
He's suffering the effects of a head wound.
无法记起过去两天发生的事情
He can't remember the events for the last 48 hours.
我就是飞到剑桥向你寻求帮助的那位 (译注: 哈佛大学位于美国剑桥市)
I'm the one who flew to Cambridge and asked for your help.
我给了你指示器 你负责解密
I gave you the pointer to decode.
兰登先生
Mr. Langdon.
我是
Yes.
好吧 我想起来了
Okay. I remember.
你是谁
Who are you?
我是教授在医院里救助时急诊室的医生
I was the ER doctor at the hospital when the Professor came in.
你最后能记起来的事情是什么
What is the last thing you remember?
我在大街上 我觉得就在这里
I was on the street. I think it was here.
还陪着位女士
I was with a woman.
- 然后被注射了东西 - 伊丽莎白·辛斯基
- And I was given an injection. - Elizabeth Sinskey.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth?
也是世卫组织的
From the World Health Organization.
你认识她么
Do you know her?
是的
I do.
但我好几年没见过她了
But I haven't seen Elizabeth in years.
她就是我单独跟着你们的原因
She's the reason I followed you alone.
你的意思是
What do you mean?
我相信辛斯基博士正与外国政府协作
I believe Dr. Sinskey is working with a foreign government
在合力寻找并外销病毒
to find and sell the virus.
不不不 那不可能
No. No. No. That's not possible.
人是会变的 教授
People change, Professor.
我已经追捕贝特朗·佐布里斯特两年了
I've been chasing Bertrand Zobrist for 2 years.
一直有人在竭力反对我
And someone has been working against me.
咱们讲重点 你知道病毒在哪里吗
Let's get to the point. You know where the virus is?
我猜你应该有身份证明吧
I assume you have some sort of credentials.
要问WHO的话你请便
Call WHO if you like.
查一下我 但动作快点
Check me out, but do it quickly.
威尼斯 我觉得在威尼斯
Venice. We think it's Venice.
很好
Good.
坐火车要两小时 跟我来吧
It's 2 hours by train. Come on.
如果我能找到你 别人也可以
If I could find you, so can the others.
我给你们都买张去日内瓦的机票
I'm buying you both plane tickets to Geneva.
不 不是日内瓦 他说是威尼斯
No, not Geneva. He said Venice.
我听到了
I heard that.
让一下 请大家注意
Excuse us. Please watch yourselves.
请退后 让一下
Step back, please. Excuse us.
让一下
Excuse us.
请大家注意
Watch yourself, please.
- 这是飞日内瓦的班机吗 - 是的 不过登机口刚刚关闭了
- This is the plane to Geneva? - Yes, but we just closed the door.
让飞机待那别动 我们要检查全部乘客
Keep the plane at the gate. We need to check every passenger.
那就是在浪费时间了
That would be a waste of time.
而且我们的时间很紧
And we have very little of that.
前往威尼斯的Italo 9982次动车 下午 1:57
三天前 在历经两年的追查后 我们找到了佐布里斯特
3 days ago, after 2 years of searching, I found Zobrist.
他然后自杀了 但我们在他口袋里找到一个包裹
He killed himself. But we took a package from his pocket.
里面是什么
And what was in it?
装有"地狱图"的法拉第指示器
The Faraday pointer with the map of hell.
是一个谜题 专门为其拥护者解谜而设计的
A puzzle, specifically designed for his followers to solve.
我们把它交给了你
We brought it to you.
你正在解密的时候
And you were in the process of decoding it,
被人给绑架了
when you were kidnapped.
兰登教授
Professor Langdon.
- 你当时跟辛斯基博士在一块 - 伊丽莎白 对的
- You were with Dr. Sinskey at the time. - Elizabeth, yes.
她有没有向你透露任何对病毒感兴趣的第三方组织
Did she tell you about any third party interest in the virus?
- 不记得了 - 她在经济上是不是有困难
- I don't remember. - Did she have financial problems?
呃 我不知道
Uh, I don't know.
她有没有带着备用手机
Did she carry more than one cellphone?
不知道
I don't know.
- 想一下 - 他不记得了
- Think. - He doesn't remember.
那就告诉我谁能记得 教授 "不知道 不记得" 真是够了
Then tell me who can remember, Professor! Enough with the "I don't know, I don't remember."!
这样对他不好
It's not good for him.
那个"金碧辉煌的博学园"是在威尼斯圣马可大教堂内
The "gilded museum" is that Saint Mark's.
整个威尼斯都是博学园
All of Venice is a museum.
那儿有"圣马尔谷之马"雕塑 它们都是铜像
St. Mark's has the Horses of Constantinople, they're bronze statues.
我可以看看吗
Can I see that?
是我我就不会碰它
I wouldn't touch it.
我也不打算那样
I wasn't planning on it.
教授
Professor.
兰登教授
Professor Langdon.
是我
Yes.
你好 罗伯特
Hello, Robert.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
好久不见
It's been a long time.
太久了
Too long.
是什么风把你吹来了
What brings you here?
WHO需要你的帮助
The WHO needs your help.
我的帮助
My help?
我希望你还记得但丁
I hope you still remember your Dante.
刚刚发生了什么
What just happened?
你还好吗
Are you alright?
你能弄点水吗 他可能脱水了
Could you get some water? He could be dehydrated.
弄点吃的 或者水果 或者列车上别的什么
Some food, maybe some fruit or something from the machine.
- 快点 - 好的
- Quickly. - Sure.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 他在撒谎吗 - 他在撒谎
- Is he lying? - Through his teeth.
他不是那天来找我的人
He was not the one who came to Cambridge to see me.
布沙尔 快来帮我 快点 我觉得他虚脱了
Bouchard, I need help, quickly. I think he's collapsed.
这门我打不开
I can't open the door.
兰登
Langdon?
你还好吗
Are you okay?
兰登 你还好吗
Langdon, are you okay?
快点 咱们走
Come on, let's go!
你在告诉我过去两年来
You're telling me that for 2 years,
你和你的组织都在跟我作对吗
you and your organization have been working against me.
没错
That is correct.
掩饰贝特朗·佐布里斯特和他的研究
To shield Bertrand Zobrist and his research.
- 藏着他 保护他 - 很遗憾 是的
- To hide him, to protect him. - Regrettably, yes.
而我全部的 避免他引发全球性流行病的尝试
And that all of my attempts to prevent him from initiating
都因为你们在从中作梗而失败了
a worldwide pandemic have failed because of you.
简单概括的话 是的
An incisive sum-up, yes.
现在你又冒冒失失的跑来 要求我相信你
Now you have the temerity to ask that I simply decide to trust you?
非常抱歉 在我看来 别无他法
I'm terribly sorry, I didn't see any other way.
你的团队 到底是干什么的
Who exactly does your group work for?
当然是服务于客户
Our clients, of course.
我们是一家私人安保公司 运作得很成功
We are a private security firm. A very successful one.
我可以请问一下
May I ask,
之前与你共事的那位绅士 布沙尔探员
the gentleman who was with you, agent Bouchard,
他现在在哪儿
where is he now?
我们不得而知 他已经失去行踪了
We don't know. We lost track of him.
那么现在的情况要比你们想像的还糟
Then the situation is worse than you think.
只有唯一一种原因会令他选择失联
There is only one reason he would move out of contact,
他想要独自找到兰登先生
he wants Mr. Langdon to himself.
为什么
Why?
找到病毒 然后再抬价转手 我猜的
To find the virus and sell it to the highest bidder I assume.
借贷收购 敲诈勒索 你懂的 老一套
Leverage, blackmail, you know, the usual shit.
我觉得咱们不必再深入讨论了 西姆斯先生
I don't think we have anything further to discuss, Mr. Sims.
寻找病原体的时间已经不足8小时 抱歉
And I have less than 8 hours to find this pathogen, excuse me.
据我所知 在此之前你就认识教授
From what I understand, you knew the Professor sometime ago.
有过私交
Personally.
你在乎他
You care about him.
你甚至会为了保护他 而跟像我这种不择手段的人合作 不是吗
You would even ally with an unscrupulous character
such as myself to protect him, wouldn't you?
我的组织就有找到兰登教授的资源
My organization has the resources to find your Professor.
威尼斯 意大利 下午 2:49
若你想要散播瘟疫 这儿就是理想之地
If you wanted to start a plague, this is where you do it.
没错
Yep.
这儿每年有两千万游客来自全球各地的游客
20 million people a year come here from every corner of the globe.
14世纪黑死病肆虐期间 威尼斯人号令全部船只
During the Black Death, the Venetians made all the ships
在港口抛锚停泊40天
anchored in the harbor for 40 days,
随后才允许船员入城
before they would allow the crews into the city.
以确保瘟疫不会传入城内
Making sure that they were not carrying the Plague.
英文中"隔离"一词就是来自意大利语
The word "Quarantine" comes from the Italian.
还有"四十" 来自"Quaranta"
"quaranta", "forty".
有你陪同感觉很棒呢 教授
It's nice to have you back, Professor.
那儿 马雕在那儿 (圣马尔谷之马)
There, the horses.
都是复制品 原件在圣殿内部保管 (原因: 空气污染)
These were recreations, the originals are in a museum for preservation.
得赶紧了 布沙尔知道我们会到这儿
We should be quick. Bouchard knows we are coming here.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
问一下那位导游 这些雕塑的马头有没有被切下过
Ask that guide, if the heads have ever been severed from these horses?
打扰一下 打扰一下
Excuse me. Excuse me.
- 打扰一下 - 麻烦了 打扰一下
- Excuse me. - Please excuse me.
麻烦了
Please.
传说在第四次十字军东征期间(1202年 - 1204年)
According to the tale, during the Crusades,
这些马雕被威尼斯军队从拜占庭的君士坦丁堡(今伊斯坦布尔)劫走
the horses were looted from Constantinople.
马匹...
Horses...
但它们实在太大 难以装船
But they were too large to be loaded on board the ships,
所以马头被切下 随后再重新接回
so their heads were removed and reattached.
哪位总督干的
By whom?
那位长生不老的总督 恩里科·丹多洛 (第41任威尼斯总督)
The doge who lived forever, Enrico Dandolo.
- 恩里科·丹多洛 - 长生不老的总督
- Enrico Dandolo. - The doge who lived forever.
当然了 恩里科·丹多洛
Of course, Enrico Dandolo.
丹多洛把威尼斯人骗入十字军中
Dandolo tricked the Venetians into the Crusades.
他原本应当率众前往埃及 却跑去把君士坦丁堡给洗劫了
He was supposed to sail his ships to Egypt, but he sacked Constantinople instead.
我很抱歉 当然是他了
I'm sorry. Of course.
"金碧辉煌的神圣智慧博学园"
"The gilded museum of holy wisdom."
我们找错了教堂吗
Are we in the wrong basilica?
我们找错了国家
We're in the wrong country.
丹多洛逝世后 并没有埋葬在此
Dandolo passed, but he was not buried here.
那他葬在哪里
So where was he buried?
圣索菲亚大教堂
Hagia Sophia.
- 伊斯坦布尔 - 伊斯坦布尔 (土耳其)
- Istanbul. - Istanbul.
总会有出路的
There's always a way out.
在这儿 这儿
Here. Here.
看看你能不能把那个打开来
See if you could get that open.
我抓住你的脚了
I got your foot.
能搞定吗
Can you get it?
外头有人吗
Is there someone there?
请帮一下
Please help.
对 对
Yes.
拉我一把
Give me a hand.
- 100块 - 好的 好的
- One hundred. - Yes! Yes.
- 100欧元 - 给 我有 我有的
- A hundred euro. - Here. I got it. I got it.
快 快 快
Quick. Quick. Quick.
谢谢
Thank you.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你说过他是个谋杀犯 是个精神变态
You called him a murderer, a psychopath.
什么
What?
但历史会把我们视为救世主
But history will call us saviors.
天呐 我的天呐
Oh my god. Oh my god.
我不怕死 罗伯特
I'm not afraid to die, Robert.
但无所事事才是令我害怕的
But doing nothing terrifies me.
指引 指示器 他是要留给你的 佐布里斯特
The path, and the pointer, he left that all for you, Zobrist.
- 你认识他吗 - 何止认识
- You knew him? - Knew him?
我爱他
I loved him.
你这套衣服就是他的
You're wearing his suit.
不 西恩娜 不
No. Sienna, no.
谢谢你 罗伯特
Thank you, Robert.
谢谢你做的一切
Thank you for everything.
不 不 西恩娜 不要
No. No. Sienna, no.
西恩娜
Sienna!
不 西恩娜 西恩娜 不要
No, Sienna! Sienna, no!
慢点 慢点 你太快啦
Slow down, slow down. You're too fast.
噢 拜托 拜托
Oh, come on. Come on.
这个费了我三天时间
This took me 3 days.
太简单啦
Too easy.
"镀金时代" - 马克·吐温
"The Gilded Age" by Mark Twain
我很喜欢
I love it.
认识你之前
Everything before you exist,
完美生活还是臆想
an idea.
如今已经成真了
And now it's real.
爱 让 灵魂 复苏
Love awaken the soul to act.
这可不公平 拿但丁来比喻我
That's not fair. Quoting Dante to me.
不过诗句里是"美" 而不是"爱"
But it's beauty, not love.
怎么了
What?
离午夜还差一分钟
It's a minute to midnight.
比我预想的还要早
Sooner than I expected.
我们要去哪
Where're we going?
噢
Oh.
我明白了
I see.
我们一同策划 一同构思
We planned it together, we designed it together,
但这部分只有你才知晓
but this part only belongs to you.
你不知道在哪 才会更安全
It's just safer if you don't know where.
如果他们抢先找到了你呢
What if they find you first?
那时怎么办
What then?
如果你想知道 你也不是一个人
If you want to know, you're not alone.
你得开始相信我
You got to start by trusting me.
我们若不立即采取大胆行动
Unless we take bold immediate action
第六次大灭绝就会轮到我们头上
the sixth extinction will be our own.
你说得对
You were right.
我要给你安排另一条路
I'm going to make you another path.
地狱也在尽头
Inferno will be at the end.
如果我遇到不测 第一条线索就会发给你
If something should happen to me, the first clue will be deliver to you.
我知道你会做好必须要做的事情
I know you'll do what must to be done.
寻找 就寻见
Seek and find.
你不是一个人
You're not alone.
那么
So.
漂亮的小妮子跑去找坏家伙了
The beautiful young woman went for the bad guy.
这事常常发生
That happens.
你看着好失望呢
You look disappointed.
我先让你缓一缓
I'll give you a minute.
伊丽莎白并非是想要转卖病毒的人
Elizabeth is not the one who wants the virus to sell.
那人是你
You are.
你被人利用了
You've been used.
有人在精心计划 驱使你为他们效力
Elaborate schemes created by people to get you to do what they want.
至于我
But me,
我就简单粗暴了
I'm very direct.
现在我正掌握一个绝佳的机会
And this is a moment of great opportunity for me.
所以 病毒在哪里
So, where is the virus?
拜托 教授
Come on, Professor.
人世间生命几何
How much life is there in the world?
有多少生来就在困苦挣扎
How much more is fighting to be born?
偶尔自相残杀也并无过错
Nothing wrong with thinning the herd once in a while.
很正常
It's healthy.
我已见过许多天意
I've seen many acts of god.
我是说 台风 霍乱 你知道吗
I mean, typhoons, cholera. And you know what?
有时候带走的 还是善人之命
Sometimes it hits the right people.
- 惨无人性 - 人之常情本就是不人道的
- That's inhuman. - Humanity is inhuman.
人命或许轻贱 但从未有人停止过
Life maybe cheap, but the means to end it on a mass scale,
探求灭绝众生的方法手段
no one ever stops paying for that.
我再最后问你一...
I'm going to ask you for the last...
万分抱歉
Terribly sorry.
没别的法子了
Didn't see any other way.
须得迅雷不及掩耳 见血越少 效果越好
Must do this quickly. The less blood the better.
你是哪位
Who are you?
噢 一名协作者
Oh, a facilitator.
除了别的业务 我们公司还制造幻觉
Among other things my company creates illusions.
你的头部并没有受伤
You never had a real head wound.
- 但我失忆了 - 是化学作用
- But I lost my memory. - Chemically induced.
我们给你注射的是苯二氮䓬类药物 (精神药物)
We gave you an injection of benzodiazapenes.
抱歉 会伴有皮疹 一两天后就消退
Sorry, it can produce a skin rash. It should fade in a day or so.
这些都是...
All this was a...
这些都是假的吗
All this was a fake?
我更喜欢制造真实感
I prefer created reality.
我的手下绑架了你
My agents kidnapped you.
为了触发全新的剧情 他们消去了你的记忆
They cleared your memories so we could create a fresh scenario,
由此你便投身于协助我们的思路中
whereby you would be invested in the idea of helping us.
我们在你头皮上划了一道小口子 这是枪击幻觉的一部分
A small incision was made in your scalp to give the impression of a bullet graze.
医院里的门也是假锁的
There are no locks on hospital doors.
没错
Exactly.
满分回答
Highest marks.
医院里杀人的那位女警察呢
What about the policewoman who shot the Doctor in the hospital?
也是我的人
Also it's me.
她的枪里是空包弹
Her gun fired blanks.
门上则有爆炸伪造的枪击效果
And there were squibs in the door.
医生是演员 身上挂着袋血浆包
The doctor was an agent wearing a blood packet.
出租车司机 整个医院都是咱们的人
The taxi driver, the hospital was working for us as well.
在旧宫里她试图要杀了我
At the Palazzo Vecchio she tried to kill me.
那是真枪实弹
It was real bullets.
我要求的
At my behest.
当事情快要败露时
When things that appeared to go tits up
我会试图赶紧杀人灭口 毁尸灭迹
I try to sweep it all away quickly.
所以要杀我
By killing me?
我深表歉意 兰登先生
I apologize unreservedly, Mr. Langdon.
我的确失去了一名老部下
I did lose an experienced agent.
这个行当里 我见过的情况够多了
There's a great deal of situation I've been informed in my line of work.
瞧 我知道的就这些
Look, hear me what I know.
我知道我看着很渗人
I know I've behaved terribly.
但谜题需要破解 这一点你最棒了
But a puzzle needed solving, who better to solve it than you.
瞟一眼 好吗
Glance at it, will you?
干得差强人意了
Not my best work.
但足以应付意大利人
But it will do for the Italians.
西恩娜来找我求助的时候 佐布里斯特早已拥趸者众
Zobrist had followers everywhere when Sienna first came to me for help.
至少我是这么认为的
Or so I thought.
佐布里斯特死后不久 她就很严肃地找上门来
She came to us with serious concerns shortly after Zobrist died.
不知怎的 她知道了我们受雇于佐布里斯特
Somehow, she knew Zobrist had hired us.
她表示这位富翁的生物研究成果 可能已经落到坏人手中
She said he was doing biological work that could be fallen into the wrong hands.
她并未提及瘟疫 但我们已经开始警惕
She didn't mention a plague. But we heard enough to be alarmed.
于是我们同意协助她 找到佐布里斯特的计划
So we agreed to work with her to find Zobrist's project.
然后当辛斯基博士带你来时 我们看到了机会
And when Dr. Sinskey brought you in, we saw an opportunity.
当时是伊丽莎白来找我的
It was Elizabeth who came to see me.
是的
Yes.
从布沙尔探员手上 辛斯基博士弄到了法拉第指示器
Dr. Sinskey got the Faraday pointer from agent Bouchard.
她带去让你解密
She brought it to you to decode,
甚至用你的指纹来设作密码
and she even secured it with your thumbprint.
我们别无选择
That left us with no choice,
所以我们在街上把你抢了过来
so we took you from her on the street.
医院里的情况促使你相信布鲁克斯医生
The hospital scenario encouraged you to trust Dr. Brooks.
你们给领事馆打电话时 另一头接通的是我们
When you called to the Consulate it was answered by our man.
兰登教授
Professor Langdon?
谢天谢地你还活着 我们一直在找你
Thank heavens you're alive. We've been looking for you.
东西你还带着吗
Are you still in possession?
你带着指示器 我们跟着你
You had the pointer and we had you.
一切都推进的天衣无缝 直到布鲁克斯女士把你引开
It was all working seamlessly until Miss. Brooks stole you away.
以确保病毒得以释放
To make sure the virus is released.
看来
It appears.
年轻人很失望
Young people are disappointing.
我发现他们35岁左右时 就挺有耐性的了
I find them become tolerable around 35.
你提到过辛斯基博士
You mentioed Dr. Sinskey.
我一直很担心你
I've been so worried.
你还好吗
Are you alright?
- 我很好 - 是吗
- I'm fine. - Are you?
我很好
I'm okay.
挺好的
I'm alright.
谢天谢地
Thank god.
- 你知道病毒在哪儿吗 - 伊斯坦布尔
- Do you know where the virus is? - Istanbul.
世界卫生组织专机 下午 5:32
现在正是时候
Now's the time.
今天是重生之日
Today is rebirth.
地狱就是救赎
Inferno is salvation.
我很抱歉把你卷进来 罗伯特
I am so sorry I brought you into this, Robert,
- 在这么多年之后 - 没事 我很高兴你那么做了
- after all these years. - No. I'm glad you did.
我见过他 佐布里斯特 两年前
I met him, you know. Zobrist, 2 years ago.
他当时向我求助
He asked for my help.
他想让WHO支持他的行动
He wanted the WHO to endorse mass sterilization
对饮用水和主食中进行大规模杀菌消毒
in drinking waters and staple foods.
于是我下了逐客令 把他列为监控对像
So I threw him out of my office, put him on the watch list.
但他失踪了...
But he disappeared and...
我猜那就是他雇佣了西姆斯的时候
I suppose that's when Zobrist hired Sims.
我早应该发... 我不知道
I should probably have... have I don't know.
怎么
What?
这些都不是你的错 你总要为它们责怪自己
You always blame yourself for things that weren't your fault.
嘴还是很甜
Still very sweet.
这边 有个门口
Here, a doorway.
我希望见面那会 是别的事情呢
I wish it would have happened differently, back then.
咱们当时没有经营好 就这么散了
We didn't look after it. It fell apart.
这算是后悔吗
Is that a regret?
我想起来的时候才会这样
Only when I think about it.
你知道吗 在门口那发生的最有意思的事情是
You know, the most interesting things happened in doorways,
那样一种持续的临界状态
at the borders, right along the edges.
古代渔民会在寒暖洋流交汇处打渔
Ancient fishermen learned to sail where the warm water met the cold.
小鱼会滞留在暖流边上
The little fish would reach the edge of the warm water and they stopped.
然后大鱼就从寒流里游过来 把它们吃掉
And the big fish would come out of the cold water and they eat them.
最后是渔民们
And the fishermen.
嗯 渔翁得利
Well, they caught everybody.
门口那儿
Doorways.
你还是老样子 罗伯特
Not one part of you has changed, Robert.
话痨一个
You talk too much.
嗯 一点也没变
And then, not at all
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
我无法请求你别去日内瓦
I couldn't ask you not to go to Geneva.
做不到
I couldn't.
我也不想让你离开剑桥市
I didn't want to ask you to leave Cambridge.
事情就是这么发生的吗
Was that how it happened?
我不能再相信记忆了
I don't trust my memory anymore.
我从未忘记任何事情
I never forget anything.
好吧 那是天赋
Well, that's a gift.
不 不是的
No, it isn't.
离他远点 嘿 嘿 你们在干嘛
Leave him alone! Hey! Hey! What are you doing?
离他远点
Leave him alone!
转过身去
Turn around!
别看我 贱货 转过头去
Don't look at me, bitch, look away!
住手
Stop it!
别看
Don't look!
罗伯特
Robert!
伊斯坦布尔 土耳其 傍晚 6:39
谢谢你
Thank you.
伊斯坦布尔大学
我是诗人的朋友
I'm a friend of the poet.
佐布里斯特为之舍身的是
For what did Zobrist die?
保全他人得生
That others may live.
我千里迢迢赶来 是要保证一切顺利进行
I've come very far to make sure nothing interferes.
我们设计好的传送系统 会在今晚午夜释放病毒药剂
The delivery system we designed will discharge the viral agent by midnight tonight.
但是有人正赶来要阻止这一切
But there are others who are on their way to stop it.
我得抢先找到它
I need to find it before they do
引爆炸弹 确保病毒被释放
and trigger an explosion to ensure it's released.
我们如何帮忙
How do we help?
在查士丁尼大瘟疫期间
During the Plague of Justinian,
伊斯坦布尔每天有5000人死于街头
5000 people died everyday in the streets in Istanbul.
东西方交流的又一个门户
A border between East and West, another doorway.
这是他选中此地的原因
Which is why he chose it.
如果袋子没有破损 我们可以装住它
If the bag is intact, we can contain it.
但若有人先发制人 把它弄破了
But if someone ruptures it before we get there
47天内 95%的地球人口会受感染
95% of the earth's population will be infected in 47 days.
圣索菲亚大教堂 傍晚 7:53
教授 博士
Professor. Doctor.
我是米尔沙特 这儿的负责人
My name is Mirsat, I'm the curator here.
你有没有彻底疏散建筑内的人群
Have you completely evacuated the building?
我们竭尽全力了 但这地方实在太大
Well, to the extent that we can but the place is massive.
你可以告诉我要找的东西具体是什么吗
Could you tell me specifically what it is you're looking for?
恩里科·丹多洛之墓
The tomb of Enrico Dandolo.
好的 这边请
Of course, this way.
"跪在金碧辉煌的神圣智慧博学园内
"Kneel within the gilded museum of holy wisdom,
聆听小溪的流水声"
and listen for the sounds of trickling water."
"下到水下宫殿深处"
"Follow deep into the sunken palace."
我听到地面下有流水声
I hear water flowing under these stones.
它流向哪儿
Where does it go?
只是个排水道 流入到市政蓄水池里
It's just drainage. It goes to the city cistern.
我们要找的是一个大型地下空间
We're looking for a large, underground space,
内部可能有支柱和人工照明
perhaps with columns, artificially lit from within.
那简单 古人的供水系统
That's simple. The ancient system,
16世纪 沉没的宫殿
sixth century, Yerebatan Sarayi.
也被称为"地下水宫殿"
Also called, "The sunken palace."
带我们去那儿
Take us there.
他的话只会对应一样东西
His words can only mean one thing.
沉没的宫殿 地下水宫殿
Yerebatan Sarayi. The Sunken Palace.
咱们下去后 你就会看到了
Once we descend, you'll see exactly what he described.
这个怎么用
How do I use it?
爆炸物装在接线盒里
There's a cap in the padial integrate.
爆炸装置也有个引爆按钮
The device also has a detonation button.
去个电话 就会引爆
A call from this cellphone will trigger the explosion.
这么点就能弄破袋子吗
And that's enough to break the bag?
四面墙壁都是混凝土
The walls are cement all around.
这俩炸弹都要装上 两个角度 尽量分开
You need both bombs, different angles, as far apart as you can.
然后就能弄破袋子
That's what break the bag.
史书认为黑死病带来了苦难和死亡
History says that the Black Plague caused misery and death.
但并没有告知我们
But, what they don't tell us,
它也同样精简了人口 并孕育了文艺复兴运动
is that it also produced a leaner population, and gave birth to the Renaissance.
我们正在全速奔向地狱的第七层
We are rushing as fast as we can into the seventh circle of hell.
自取灭亡 却又有利可图
Suicidal but profitable.
能够短痛 何必长痛
Why is suffering later preferable to suffering now?
倘若我们欣然接受 然后痛苦或许就能解救我们
What if we embrace it. And then maybe pain can save us.
你听明白了 对吧 我看得出来
You're getting this, aren't you? I can see that you are.
现在我想知道的是我并非形单影只
Now I need to know that I'm not alone.
人太特么多了
Too many damn people.
地方选得很好
He has chosen well.
我需要所有进出蓄水池的管道分配图
I need schematics of all conduits in and out of the cistern.
还有全面隔离和控制方案
Full isolation and containment protocols.
物理和化学屏蔽 外加... 等会
Physical and chemical barriers along with... Wait.
这是城内的供水系统吗
This is the city's water supply?
噢 现在不是了 已经现代化改造过
Oh, not anymore. We've modernized.
但里面的水就留在那儿
But there is water in there.
是的 最终慢慢渗入地下
Yes. It eventually filters down into the earth.
那为什么这么多人
But why are all these people here?
现在是旅游景点了 那儿的演出很精彩
It is a tourist attraction. The acoustics are excellent.
今晚就有夏至音乐会 很受欢迎
Tonight is the summer solstice concert, very popular.
人们从世界各地赶来 欣赏盛会
People come from all over the world to hear it.
他制造了一种生物气溶胶
He created a bioaerosol.
所以可以通过空气传播
So it will spread in the air.
- 清空现场人群 - 不要
- Empty the place. - No.
围住那儿
Contain it.
屏蔽附近所有信号 断绝信息进出
Jam all communications down there. No messages get in or out.
明白
Got it.
那我们进去吧
Shall we go in?
罗伯特 你不必陪我们进去
Robert, you don't have to go in there with us.
不 我要去的
Yes, I do.
"血红的泻湖不会倒映群星"
"Blood-red waters of the lagoon that reflects no stars."
老天爷 这儿就像个迷宫
My god, this is a labyrinth.
有多少块区域
How many sections?
有很多 教授 很多
There are dozens, Professor, dozens.
我们去找到它
Let's find it.
检查每个区域 每条柱子
Check every section, every column.
全要检查
Check them all.
散开来
Spread out.
现在切断手机信号
Cut off cellphone service now.
- 隔绝通讯 - 是 长管
- No communications. - Yes, sir.
这儿有美国的联络人 我需要帮助
Those are US contacts over here, I need some help.
这里 这边走 美杜莎
Here. This way. Medusa.
希腊神话 为什么 (译注: 美杜莎是希腊神话中的女蛇妖)
The Greek spirits, why?
它属于希腊神话中的一个特定种类 地府鬼神
It belongs to a specific category of Greek spirits. Chthonic monsters.
- 就这儿吗 - 是的
- This is it? - Yes.
颜色 柱子 跟视频上看到的一模一样
The color, the columns, it's exactly what we saw in the video
就是这儿了 大家散开 检查柱子
This is the area, so spread out, check the pillars.
- 我负责墙边 - 各个角落
- I'll take the wall line. - The corners.
走道下面
Under the walkway.
如有任何发现 立即向我报告
If you find anything, report to me immediately.
谁来照照这里 分秒必争
Light it here, someone. Seconds matter.
打扰一下 打扰一下
Excuse me. Excuse me.
- 发生什么事了 - 先生 请你让开
- What's going on? - Sir, I need you to step aside.
各位请回避
Step aside, everyone.
找着了 在这儿 那个角落里
I got it. It's here. In this far corner.
不要
Don't.
生化小组尚未就位
Hazmat guys aren't set yet.
我等不及了
I can't wait.
赶紧的 这玩意随时会破
Quickly! This could break any moment.
西恩娜
Sienna!
这是氮气吹洗装置 徒手操作吗
This is cube nitrogen purge. Without gloves access.
- 应该可以 - 最好如此
- It should. - It better.
西恩娜 西恩娜
Sienna. Sienna.
我们人多势众
There are too many of us down here!
你抢不到袋子的
You won't get to that bag before we do!
的确 但我会确保它破掉
No. But I can make sure it breaks.
不 别这么做 西恩娜 不要 你会滥杀无辜
No. Don't do this, Sienna, don't. You'll be murdering innocents.
没错 很多人会死去
Yes. People will die
但危机得以避免
a lot of them but the crisis will be averted.
这是大自然的旨意
It's what nature demands.
人口危机问题不再只会缓解 而是一劳永逸的解决了
The problem won't just be slowed down, it would be solved permanently.
借生灵涂炭来拯救苍生 这是暴君的逻辑
Killing billions to save lives. That's the logic of tyrants.
- 为了更高的目标 人类... - 就算天才也不能有这种权利
- For a greater good, humanity... - Geniuses don't come with extra rights.
不 他有责任去行他人所不能行之事
No, it comes with the responsibility to take action when others won't!
你想做点什么 行啊
You want to do something, fine.
那就把问题提出来 然后解决掉
Then scream at the top of your lungs. An event and leave.
如果你爱这个物种 如果你爱这个星球
If you loved humanity, if you love this planet,
你会不惜一切去挽救它
you would do anything to save it.
人类历史上那些极恶之罪都曾冠以爱的名义
The greatest sins in human history had been committed in the name of love.
但没人会赞同这种看法
No one will look on this act and call it love.
人类会延续的
They'll be alive.
别人如何评价 又与我何干
What does it matter what they say about us.
无信号
No Signal
嘿 你在干什么
Hey, what are you doing?
不可以
Don't!
别射着箱子
Don't shoot the box!
罗伯特 快闪开
Robert, get clear!
你还好吗 你没事吧
Are you alright? Are you alright?
没事
Fine.
箱子在哪 箱子在哪
Where's the box. Where's the box.
它密封了 完好无损
It's contained, no breach.
病毒已被完全隔离
The virus has been completely contained.
病毒已被隔离
The virus has been contained.
- 医疗小组全部进场 - 我们现在接管这儿的工作
- All medical team come in . - We'll take it from now on.
重复一遍 目标已被隔离 准备转移
I repeat. The target is contained, be prepared for transport.
没有泄漏 重复一遍 没有泄漏
There is no leakage. I Repeat. There is no leakage.
她以为她在拯救世界
She thought she was saving the world.
他们也是这么想的
So did they all.
那么 接下来要做什么
So, what would happen now?
我们会带回日内瓦做检测 把它隔离起来
We'll take it back to Geneva for test, put it in isolation.
首先要测出基因序列
We'll have to generate another geno sequences first
再顺藤摸瓜 提出解决方案
to get an idea what we are dealing with.
接下来还有很多事要忙
There's a lot of work to be done.
你呢 回去吗
And you, Cambridge?
是的
Yeah.
辛斯基博士
Dr. Sinskey?
生活又要把咱分开了
Life tore us apart again.
就像但丁和比阿特丽斯那样
Like Dante and Beatrice.
我有东西要给你
I have something for you.
你被绑架那晚 我捡到了这个
I picked this up the night you were taken.
我记得它对你似乎意味非凡
I seem to remember it was important to you.
是的 是的没错
Yes. Yes, it is.
你有没有想过 你我之间
Do you ever think about what could happen
会发生些什么
with you and me?
我想过
I do.
我猜生活还得有点儿神秘感 教授
I guess life must have it's mysteries, Professor,
即便是我们俩
even for us.
佛罗伦萨 意大利 某天早上 9:00
- 打扰一下 你会讲英语吗 - 会的
- ' Scusati, do you speak English? - Yes.
有没有见到玛塔·阿尔瓦雷兹 那位工作人员
Have you seen Marta Alvarez, the museum staff?
玛塔现在不在这 她怀孕了
Marta isn't here just now. She's had her baby.
她怀孕了 啊呀 太棒了
She had her baby? Aw, that is great.
好消息
Great news.
那么 你或许要通知某人该给但丁面具展位开灯了
Well, you might tell someone that the lights on the Dante mask
我几乎看不到呢
should be turned on because I can barely see it.
我很遗憾 先生 但丁面具不在这儿
I'm sorry, sir, the Dante mask is no longer here.
它被盗了
It was stolen.
- 真的吗 - 嗯 - 我刚还看着它呢
- Really? - Um - I was just looking at it.
失陪一下
Excuse me.